Finding Aid for Robert Alexander Papers 1970-1982
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Robert Alexander Papers 1970-1982
Alexander, Robert, 1945-
2.5 linear feet
Ann Arbor, Michigan political activist and campaign worker on behalf of Human Rights Party and Democratic Party candidates. Files and photographs (circa 1970-1980) relating to the Fred Harris presidential campaign in 1976, the Ed Pierce campaigns for Michigan state office in 1976, 1978, 1980 and 1982, and the Zolton Ferency campaign for governor of Michigan in 1978.
8515 Aa 2
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The papers came to the library as the gift of Robert Alexander (Donor no. 6952 ) in July 1983.
The collection is open for research.
Robert Alexander was born in 1945 and grew up in Berkeley, a suburb of Detroit. He studied Asian American history at the University of Michigan, earning his B.A. in 1966. Following his graduation, Alexander joined the Peace Corps. For two years he worked in South India in a poultry program. In 1968 he returned to the United States. From 1968 to 1971 he taught elementary school, first in southwest Kentucky, and then in Detroit's inner city. At the same time Alexander completed his M.A. in Education at Wayne State University (1970). He then moved to Ann Arbor and for four years worked at the University of Michigan in the International Student Orientation Program. Afterwards, he became a sixth grade teacher at Kaiser Elementary School in Willow Run.
As was common among students in the mid-1960's, Alexander became caught up in politics while he was at the University of Michigan. In 1964 at age nineteen, Alexander campaigned for the Ann Arbor Democratic Party. He was not active in politics again until 1971, when he joined the Human Rights Party.
The Human Rights Party (HRP) originated in 1970 when thirty-five leftist dissidents, disgusted with the Democratic Party, met in a Southfield motel to establish their own socialist democratic party. In 1972, the HRP merged with the Ann Arbor leftist organization, the Radical Independent Party (founded 1971).
The HRP was composed of a core of radical activists who sought to bring about a socialist society through the democratic electoral process. It was a statewide party, led by Zolton Ferency, one of the maverick ex-Democrats. However, the main strength of the HRP was in Ann Arbor, due to the student population. Following extensive voter registration efforts (the voting age was lowered to eighteen in 1971), the HRP elected two of its members to the Ann Arbor City Council. Thus the City Council found itself debating such issues as gay and women's rights, day care centers, decriminalization of prostitution and marijuana and the Vietnam War.
Despite this initial success, in subsequent years the HRP was weakened by dissipating student activism and a renewal of spirit in the Democratic Party. It was also rend by internal quarrels over election strategies and debates on the effectiveness of third party politics.
However, in 1974 the HRP managed to pull itself together and elect another Councilwoman. In the same election, Robert Alexander was the HRP candidate for State Representative in the 53rd District. He was defeated by Perry Bullard. After this election, the HRP elected no more candidates and in 1977 it quietly merged with the Socialist Party USA.
Alexander was disillusioned with the electoral abilities of the HRP before its ultimate demise. In April 1975 he returned to the Democratic Party and became involved in the Fred Harris for President campaign. Alexander was one of three state coordinators for Harris. At the same time, he was a volunteer on the campaign to send Ed Pierce to the State Congress. In 1977, he worked for Al Wheeler, running for Mayor of Ann Arbor. The following year Alexander was elected to the Executive Committee of the Democratic Party of Washtenaw County, and he was the state campaign coordinator for both Zolton Ferency (for Governor), and Ed Pierce (for State Senate). In 1980, deciding that Ferency was not "electable," Alexander worked for Pierce for Governor, against Ferency. Again he was a campaign coordinator.
The papers of Robert Alexander span the years 1970-1982. The primary focus of the collection is on Alexander's political activities in both the Human Rights Party and the Democratic Party. There is no personal material, nor is there documentation of Alexander's career. Even within the sections on his political activities there is only a moderate amount specifically relating to Alexander. The papers give a view of local politics, in which Alexander was a relatively minor figure.
Subjects:
Alexander, Robert, 1945-; Democratic Party (Mich.); Elections--Michigan--1976.; Elections--Michigan--1978.; Elections--Michigan--1980.; Elections--Michigan--1982.; Elections--United States.; Ferency, Zolton A., 1922-1993; Harris, Fred R., 1930-; Human Rights Party (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Michigan--Politics and government--1951-; Michigan--Politics and government--1971-1980.; Michigan--Politics and government--1981-1990.; Pierce, Edward, 1930-; Presidents--United States--Election--1976.; Radicalism--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; United States--Politics and government--1974-1977.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Alexander, Robert, 1945-; Ann Arbor (Mich.)--Politics and government.; Democratic Party (Mich.); Harris, Fred R., 1930-; Human Rights Party (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Political elections--1976.; Politics and government--1971-1980.
Genre/Form:
Photographs.
- Biographical Material
  - Miscellaneous information (Box 1)
- Human Rights Party
  The Human Rights Party series covers the years from 1971 to 1975 when Alexander left the Party. The series is subdivided into History and Constitution, Committees, Elections, Financial Material, Lists (of contributors, members, etc.), Meetings, Minutes, Newspaper Clippings, Notes (by Alexander), Platforms, Position Papers, Press Releases, Sponsored Events, Strategy and Miscellanea. The files of Newspaper Clippings includes eighteen issues of the Ann Arbor Sun, a local radical publication, as well as clippings from other local papers.
  - History and Constitution (Box 1)
  - Committees
    - Ad Hoc Committee on Representation (Box 1)
    - City Committee (Box 1)
    - Labor Committee (Box 1)
    - Platform Committee (Box 1)
    - Public Schools Committee (Box 1)
    - Steering Committee (Box 1)
  - Elections
    - Handouts and Posters, 3 folders (Box 1)
    - Paid Political Announcements (Box 1)
    - Special Publications (Box 1)
  - Financial Material (Box 1)
  - Lists (contributors, membership, etc.) (Box 1)
  - Meetings 1972-1975 (Box 1)
  - Minutes 1972-1974 (Box 1)
  - Newsletters 1972-1977 (Box 1)
  - Newsletters The Human Voice, 1973-1975 (Box 1)
  - Newspaper Clippings
    - Ann Arbor Sun, February 1972-1975, 5 folders (Box 1)
    - Others undated, 1971-1980, 4 folders (Box 1)
  - Notes of Robert Alexander (Box 1)
  - Platforms (Box 1)
  - Position Papers (Box 1)
  - Press Releases 1972-1975 (Box 1)
  - Sponsored Events (Box 1)
  - Strategy (Box 1)
  - Miscellanea (Box 1)
- Democratic Party
  The series - Democratic Party - is the largest in the collection. It documents the years 1975-1982. The largest portion of this series is Campaigns, which includes campaigns on which Alexander worked: Fred Harris for President (1976), Ed Pierce for State Congress (1976), Al Wheeler for Mayor (1977), Zolton Ferency for Governor (1978), Ed Pierce for State Senate (1978), and Ed Pierce for Governor (1980). In turn each Campaign is further divided into Campaign Strategy, Correspondence, Financial Material, Meetings, Newsletters, Notes (by Alexander), Pamphlets and Posters, Press Releases, Sponsored Events, and other categories where necessary.
  - Campaigns
    - 1976
      - Fred Harris, Presidential Campaign
        - Campaign Lists (Box 1)
        - Correspondence and Newsletters (Box 1)
        - Financial Material (Box 1)
        - Meetings (Box 1)
        - Pamphlets and Posters (Box 1)
        - Press Conference September 14, 1975 (Box 1)
        - Slide Show Notes (Box 2)
        - Sponsored Events (Box 2)
        - Working Papers (Box 2)
        - Miscellanea (Box 2)
      - Edward Pierce, Michigan State Legislature
        - Financial Material (Box 2)
        - Meetings (Box 2)
        - Newsletters (Box 2)
        - Pamphlets and Posters (Box 2)
        - Sponsored Events (Box 2)
        - Miscellanea (Box 2)
    - 1977
      - Albert Wheeler Ann Arbor Mayoralty campaign (Box 2)
    - 1978
      - Zolton Ferency gubernatorial campaign
        - Campaign Strategy (Box 2)
        - Campaign Lists (Box 2)
        - Correspondence (Box 2)
        - Ferency Committee Meetings (Box 2)
        - Finances, 2 folders (Box 2)
        - Newsletters (Box 2)
        - Notes, Robert Alexander (Box 2)
        - Pamphlets and Posters (Box 2)
        - Position Papers (Box 2)
        - Press Releases (Box 2)
        - Radio and Television (Box 2)
        - Sponsored Events (Box 2)
        - Miscellanea (Box 2)
      - Edward Pierce campaign for the State Senate
        - Campaign Strategy (Box 2)
        - Financial Material (Box 2)
        - Meetings
          - Campaign Meetings (Box 2)
          - Inner Office Meetings (Box 2)
          - Staff Meetings (Box 2)
          - Others (Box 2)
        - Newsletters (Box 2)
        - Notes, Robert Alexander (Box 2)
        - Pamphlets and Posters (Box 2)
        - Sponsored Events (Box 2)
        - Miscellanea (Box 2)
    - 1982 Edward Pierce gubernatorial campaign
      - Campaign Strategy (Box 2)
      - Correspondence (Box 2)
      - Field Updates (Box 2)
      - Financial Material, 2 folders (Box 2)
      - Issues and Statements (Box 2)
      - Meetings
        - Campaign Committee Meetings (Box 2)
        - Core Group Meetings (Box 2)
        - Staff Meetings (Box 2)
        - Steering Committee Meetings (Box 2)
        - Others (Box 2)
      - Memoranda (Box 2)
      - Newsletters (Box 2)
      - Notes, Robert Alexander, 2 folders (Box 2)
      - Pamphlets and Posters (Box 3)
      - Press Releases (Box 3)
      - Radio and Television (Box 3)
      - Schedules (Box 3)
      - Sponsored Events (Box 3)
      - Miscellanea (Box 3)
  - Chapters
    - Ann Arbor (Box 3)
    - Washtenaw County (Box 3)
- Other Materials
  The Other Materials series includes Correspondence, Democratic Socialist Party, Farmworkers Support Committee, Petitions, Voter Registration, Wilmington Ten Defense Committee and Miscellanea. With the exception of Voter Registration, which is moderately sized, these files are all quite small and they are of the least importance to the collection as a whole.
  - Correspondence
    - Undated-1976 (Box 3)
    - 1977-1982 (Box 3)
  - Democratic Socialist Party (Box 3)
  - Farmworkers Support Committee (Box 3)
  - Petitions (Box 3)
  - Voter Registration
    - Guidelines and Instructions (Box 3)
    - Notes, Robert Alexander (Box 3)
    - Publicity (Box 3)
    - Registrars (Box 3)
    - Miscellanea (Box 3)
  - Wilmington Ten Defense Committee (Box 3)
  - Miscellanea (Box 3)
- Photographs
  Photographs relate to the Fred Harris for President campaign in 1976. Also included are photographs of local Ann Arbor political figures.
  - Slides re: Fred Harris for President campaign 1976 (Box 3)
  - Photographs of Ann Arbor politicians (Democratic Party and Human Rights Party) (Box 3)